Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning collection LCP.Stevens
Library Company of Philadelphia
Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning collection
1734-1982
LCP.Stevens
Library Company of Philadelphia
3.0 Linear feet
The Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning family papers document the development of a white family and a prominent middle-class African American family in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, beginning with the 1760s emigration of John Stevens from England to South Carolina. The materials date from 1734 to 1982 and consist of scrapbooks, ephemera, newspaper clippings, Common Prayer books, invitations, holiday cards, correspondence, business papers, and a variety of personal papers. The materials document the Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning families’ professional, family, and personal lives as well as the development of a prominent middle-class African American family.
Buck, Pearl S. (Pearl Sydenstricker), 1892-1973
Cogdell
Holden, Sallie Sanders Venning, 1872-1959
Jackson, Mary Hinkson, 1928-2014
Sanders
Stevens
Venning
Biographical/Historical note
The story of the Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning family, which eventually developed into a prominent middle class African American family in Philadelphia, began in the 1760s, when John Stevens emigrated from England and settled in Georgia. He began as a Georgia planter, owning a plantation until a slave rebellion ended his plantation career. After this setback, he settled in Charleston, South Carolina. There he established the Carolina Coffee House, which became an important establishment and meeting point in the community. He later received a postal appointment, which added to his success. He had a daughter, Mary Ann Elizabeth Stevens, and a son, John (Jack) Stevens. His son John (Jack) Stevens left Charleston, South Carolina and moved to Jamaica, against his father’s wishes. His daughter, Mary Ann Elizabeth Stevens, married George Cogdell.
Mary Ann Elizabeth Stevens and George Cogdell had three known sons, John Stephano Cogdell, Clements Stevens Cogdell, and Richard Walpole Cogdell. Their son, Richard Walpole Cogdell (1787-1866) married a woman named Cecilia, and they had three sons, James Gordon Cogdell, George Burgess Cogdell, and John Walpole Cogdell. Although he was married with a family, Richard Walpole Cogdell had a relationship with an enslaved woman, Sarah Martha Sanders (d. 1850). This relationship existed despite the feelings and emotions of his family, particularly his mother, about intimacies between the races. His mother, Mary Elizabeth Stevens wrote in her diary, “the laws of country are imperfect allowing such familiarity [physical intimacy between white men and black women] with impurity, every white man having such connection should be compelled by the laws of humanity to marry the person, black or mulatto, with whom such familiarities have existed, and to have no intercourse with genteel society or to appear in any public place of amusement on an equality with other citizens,” ( Library Company of Philadelphia Annual Report, p. 27). Mary Elizabeth Stevens passed before her son Richard Walpole Cogdell fathered children with Sarah Martha Sanders.
Richard Walpole Cogdell (1787-1866) would father no less than ten children with the enslaved woman Sarah Martha Sanders (Robert, Jacob, Julia E., Sarah Ann, Cordelia, John, Sophia Elizabeth, Miranda, Florence, and Martha J.). Though Richard Walpole Cogdell did not marry Sarah Martha Sanders (he was already married to Cecilia), he appeared to maintain an affectionate relationship with her and their children. He supported them financially and made provisions for them in his will. In the 1850s, Cogdell bought a house in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and arranged for his children by Sanders to move there in order flee the slave state of South Carolina. Eventually, Richard Walpole Cogdell’s estate languished due to poor fiscal management. He died in Philadelphia in 1866.
Despite Richard Walpole Cogdell’s financial misfortunes, Richard Walpole Cogdell and Sarah Martha Sanders’ children and their children’s offspring went on to join Philadelphia’s middle class black citizenry. The children became tradesmen, businessmen, educators, and business professionals. The Sanders were “...dedicated to providing their children with opportunities for education, culture and economically secure professional status,” ( Library Company of Philadelphia Annual Report, p. 28). The Sanders family was involved in several prominent local African American institutions, including the St. Thomas P.E. Church, Church of the Crucifixion, Central Presbyterian Church, the Colored Institute of Youth, and the Citizens Republic Club.
Cogdell and Sanders’ daughter Julia married a carpenter named Edward Y. Venning who was in business with his father, Edward W. Venning. Together they had ten children, Miranda, Julia Elizabeth, Cordelia Nixon, Sophia, Oliver Casey, Robert, Sallie, George Edward, Martha and Louise. Their daughter Miranda Venning became a teacher and eventually the principal of the Joseph E. Hill School. She was educated at the prestigious Institute for Colored Youth, Robert Forten's private school, and the Vaux School. She was the first black graduate of Philadelphia’s Girls Normal School in 1882. Julia and Edward Venning’s son, George Edward, married Julia Capps and Julia and Edward’s daughter Sallie Sanders married William B. Holden.
Cogdell and Sanders’ daughter Cordelia married William H. Chew, a hairdresser and wigmaker. The Chew family, in 1880, sued to abolish racially segregated schools in Pennsylvania. Cordelia and William H. Chew had two sons, Richard Sanders (1871-1962) and Charles Sanders (1873-1954). Their son Richard Sanders Chew, benefited from the Chew family efforts and Richard Sanders Chew studied engineering at the University of Pennsylvania; however, at the supposed advice of a professor there, he moved to the West Coast and lived as a white man. He married a white woman and had a successful career. Their other son, Charles Sanders Chew married Georgine Saunders and had two children, Agnes (1896-1984) and Cordelia (1897-1983).
In 1921, Cordelia Chew married Dr. DeHaven Hinkson (1891-1975), with whom she had two daughters, Cordelia “Betty” (b. 1922) and Mary (1925-2014). During World War I, DeHaven Hinkson served in the United States Army Medical Reserve Corps and, during World War II, he became the first black officer to head an Army hospital when he was assigned to the station hospital at the Tuskegee Army Air Field in Alabama. In 1951, Mary Hinkson became one of two African American dancers to join the Martha Graham Dance Company, where she danced until her retirement in 1973. Hinkson also danced with other prominent choreographers including Donald McKayle, John Butler, and Glen Tetly.
Bibliography:
“Afro-Americana: Family Values, in Black and White” in The Annual Report of the Library Company of Philadelphia for the Year 1991, pp. 26-31. Philadelphia: The Library Company of Philadelphia.
“How America Lives: Meet the Hinksons of Philadelphia, Pa.,” Ladies Home Journal, August 1942, 75-79.
Walker, M. Lorenzo. “DeHaven Hinkson, M.D., 1891-,” Journal of the National Medical Association 66, no. 4 (1974): 339-342.
Related Archival Materials note
Library Company of Philadelphia: Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning family portrait collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Cordelia H. Brown, Lillie V. Dickerson, Mary Hinkson Jackson, and Georgine E. Willis in honor of Phil Lapsansky.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research use, on deposit at the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, 1300 Locust Street, Philadelphia, PA 19107. For access, please contact the Historical Society at 215-732-6200 or visit http://www.hsp.org.
Scope and Contents note
The Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning family papers document the development of a white family and a prominent middle class African American family in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, beginning with the 1760s emigration of John Stevens from England to South Carolina. The papers consist of seven series: “Stevens family papers,” “Cogdell family papers,” “Sanders family papers,” “Venning family papers,” “Unattributed family papers,” “Scrapbook materials and related ephemera,” and "Hinkson family papers." The materials date from 1734 to 1976 and consist of scrapbooks, ephemera, newspaper clippings, Common Prayer books, invitations, holiday cards, correspondence, business papers, and a variety of personal papers. The materials document the Stevens-Cogdell-Sanders-Venning families’ professional, family, and personal lives.
The series “Stevens family papers” consists of two of John Stevens’ letter books that date from October 20, 1768 to January 11, 1772. The series is arranged in chronological order. The letter books contain over 160 handwritten letters and depict his business activities and daily life at his Carolina Coffee House. Many of the letters are written to his son Jack, chastising him for his irresponsible move to Jamaica, or to other correspondents in Jamaica, including associates of his son. These letter books are an interesting glimpse into the relationship of the father and son. There are also a variety of letters to associates and family in Charleston, London, and Savannah.
The series “Cogdell family papers” is comprised of materials from John Steven’s daughter, Mary Anne Elizabeth Stevens and her husband George Cogdell, and two of their three sons, John Stephens Cogdell and Richard Walpole Cogdell. Most of the materials relate to Richard Walpole Cogdell. This series contains receipt books, indentures for land in Georgetown and South Carolina, militia papers, correspondence and wills. The series is arranged in chronological order. Of interest is the diary of Mary Anne Elizabeth Stevens, which contains quotations, poems and writing regarding the mixing of the races. The commonplace books with Richard Walpole Cogdell’s materials consist of business correspondence and Cogdell’s papers compiled by a future family member into a scrapbook volume that contains sheet music and engineering exercises. Included in the volumes are Richard Walpole Cogdell’s directions to the executors of his estate and his children after his death as well as a letter from his son Charles Stevens regarding money. The will of Richard Walpole Cogdell reflects the sentiment that he felt towards Sarah Martha Sanders, and shows the provisions and inheritance that he left for his second family after his death. There are also a number of letters that portray his affection to his children in the Sanders family.
The “Sanders family papers” series is comprised of papers relating to the Sanders family, the Chew family and the Saunders family. People documented within the series are Sarah Martha Sanders, Sarah Anne Sanders, Mary E. Saunders, and Georgine Saunders Rex. The papers date from 1852 to 1892 and are arranged in chronological order. The series contains account information, business papers, pew receipts, correspondence, visiting cards and newspaper clippings. There are numerous papers relating to Richard Walpole Cogdell’s death and assets. The papers reflect the business transactions of the family and their existence in the African American middle class community. The papers also show the community involvement of the family through their pew receipts and numerous music recital clippings regarding Mary E. Saunders.
The series “Venning family papers” contains papers from the Venning family, the Holden family, and the Capp family. The series dates from 1830 to 1976. The papers include religious documents, birth certificates, documents relating to education, correspondence, obituaries, financial records, broadsides, invitations, programs, pamphlets and Valentine’s Day cards. The series is arranged in chronological order. Of interest is Edward Y. Venning’s “freedom papers,” from 1830, in which a white Charlestonian vouches for his character in a letter of recommendation. An account book by Edward Y. Venning provides information on his construction activities in Philadelphia. The papers of Edward W. Venning include a military draft paper relating to the substitute he afforded to fight in his place in the Civil War, John Diggs. The papers of Miranda Venning include newspaper clippings relating to her education and career, an autograph book, receipts, and school reports. Miranda Cogdell Venning’s newspaper clippings reflect the history of black education. Of note, are rare newspaper clippings from black newspapers, such as the Philadelphia Tribune, that are not known to have been preserved in any other collection. Numerous pamphlets, brochures, and invitations reflect the family’s activities in Philadelphia. For related materials on the Venning family, consult the series “Scrapbook Materials and Related Ephemera.”
The fifth series, “Unattributed family papers,” is comprised of papers that cannot be attributed to any particular family. The series dates from 1792 to circa 1915 and is arranged in chronological order. It consists of Common Prayer books, business cards and newspaper clippings.
The sixth series, “Scrapbook materials and related ephemera,” contains a variety of materials collected by family members that were previously placed in a scrapbook as well as complete scrapbooks. The series is arranged in chronological order and dates from 1851 to 1941, with the exception of three complete scrapbooks and photocopies of scrapbooks placed at the end of the series. Much of the ephemera and scrapbook materials were removed from pages of a scrapbook and the original order is not known. Most of the materials were most likely collected by the Venning family; however, the materials contain information on numerous other families. Most notable are Miranda Venning’s scrapbooks and the ephemera. The ephemera present in this series documents numerous events that the family was invited to, participated in or attended, reflecting the family’s prominence and involvement in the African American community of Philadelphia. There are numerous documents and ephemera relating to church events, organization events, musical events, and educational events. Miranda Venning’s scrapbooks also contain numerous materials related to Philadelphia music history, including articles and materials related to Marion Anderson, as well as numerous items related to the education system and the black community. The scrapbooks include various black newspapers clippings, including those of the Philadelphia Tribune.
The seventh series, “Hinkson family papers,” contains papers from and about the Chew family and the Hinkson family. The bulk is comprised of correspondence from Mary Hinkson to her parents while on tour in Europe with the Martha Graham Dance Company. Also notable is correspondence from Pearl Buck to Cordelia Chew Hinkson and a typescript of Buck’s 1942 article “The Dark Shadow,” which described the racial prejudice that the Hinksons faced in Philadelphia and was declined for publication by the Ladies Home Journal.
The Library Company also holds a “Steven-Cogdell and Sanders-Venning family portrait collection” in its prints and photograph department. The photographs are mostly Venning family portraits, but there are also portraits of the Cogdell family and the Capps family. There are group portraits of the Venning family participating in the Philadelphia music community, the Venning family participating in numerous organizations, Venning family vacation photographs, Venning family graduation photographs, and photographs of Mary Hinkson's travels in Europe while touring with the Martha Graham Dance Company in the 1950s. For more information on this collection contact the Library Company’s prints and photographs department.
This collection holds a variety of materials and information that would be useful for a multitude of scholarly purposes. The collection, although piecemeal, would serve as appropriate supplementary material to the study of the African American middle class community of Philadelphia and its organizations, activities, and struggles. The collection depicts the struggles of the African American middle class in education, especially the areas of the collection documenting Miranda Venning. The collection also provides information on African American music community in Philadelphia during the late-nineteenth and early-twentieth centuries.
Separated Materials note
This collection contains material that has been catalogued separately and is stored in the Print Department of the Library Company of Philadelphia. This material can be found by searching in the Library Company's online catalog, WolfPAC.
Bolivar, William C.; Chew, Cordelia Sanders; Chew, Richard Sanders; Chew, William H.; Citizens' Republic Club.; Cogdell, Mary Elizabeth Stevens; Cogdell, Richard Walpole, 1787-1866; Hinkson, Cordelia Chew; Hinkson, DeHaven; Institute for Colored Youth (Philadelphia, Pa.).; Martha Graham Dance Company.; Philadelphia Tribune.; Sanders, Robert; Sanders, Sarah, d. 1850; Venning, Edward Y.; Venning, Julia Sanders; Venning, Miranda Cogdell; African American dancers; African American educators; African American history; Business records; Clippings; Correspondence; Ephemera; Family papers; Letter books; Philadelphia (Pa.); Racially mixed people; Scrapbooks
- Series I. Stevens family papers
  - Stevens, John: Letterbooks, 1768 October 20 - 1770 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II. Cogdell family papers
  - Stevens, John: Letterbook, 1770 September 11-January 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Land Indentures, mostly to John Cogdell, 1734-1930 (Box 8, Folder 16, Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cogdell, Mary Ann Elizabeth Stevens: Watercolor with poem by Cordelia Sanders on back, circa 1800, 1840 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: South Carolina state militia papers, 1802-1844 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Cogdell, Mary Ann Stevens: Diary and copybook, 1805-1823 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Three receipt books and one receipt/travel book, 1808-1845 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Correspondence, 1818-1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Visiting card, invitations and passport, 1822, 1858-1865 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Commonplace book with materials mounted in volume with sheet music, 1834-1865, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Free-Masons membership certificate, 1839; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Certificate for State Society of Cincinnati, circa 1839 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Cogdell, John Stevens, Richard Walpole Cogdell, and Louise S. Venning: Wills, 1847-1921 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Commonplace book with mostly correspondence tipped into a printed music volume, 1856-1867 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Correspondence, 1860-1866 (Box 8, Folder 18, Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Cogdell, Richard Walpole: Estate papers, 1866-1868 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III. Sanders family papers
  - Sanders-Saunders family papers: Visiting cards, letters, receipts and newspaper clippings, 1852-1871 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Saunders, Sarah: Cemetery subscriptions, South Carolina, 1843 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Sanders, Cordelia: Scrapbook, circa 1860 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Sanders, Sarah: Gift album, circa 1865 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sanders, Sarah Ann: Letters, pew receipts and papers related to estate of her father Richard Walpole Cogdell, 1867-1868 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chew family papers, 1876-1879 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rex, Georgine Sanders: Common Prayer book from William H. Chew, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Saunders, Mary E.: Recital newspaper clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series IV. Venning family papers
  - Venning, Edward Y. and Edward W.: Personal papers, 1830-1904 (Box 8, Folder 19, Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Venning and Capps families: Bills in equity, 1937, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Venning, Edward J.: Family bible (originally owned by Sarah Martha Sanders), 1852 (Oversize *Am 1851 Big Eng 17021.Q (SCSVC))
  - Venning Family: Valentines cards, 1854, 1857, 1938, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Holden family: Stock certificates and business correspondence, 1860-1930 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Venning, Miranda C.: Birth certificate, educational papers, correspondence and obituaries, 1862-1900 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Venning family baptism records, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Venning, George De Reef: Account book and receipt, 1874-1906 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Venning family Holy Bible with obituaries tipped in., 1877 (Object Am 1877 Bib Eng 113279.D (SCSVC))
  - Venning, Miranda C.: Autograph book, 1877-1886 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Venning, Miranda C.: Diploma for Girls Normal School, 1882; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Venning, Sallie Sanders: Autograph album, 1886 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Venning, George: Diploma for Industrial SAA School, 1889 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Venning, Miranda: Scrapbook (includes original and photocopy of scrapbook, circa 1890; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Venning, Sallie Sanders: Diaries (3), 1890-1892 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Venning, Miranda: William Carl Bolivar "Hash Book" and related papers, 1893-1914 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Venning family papers relating to death of family members, 1894-1897 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Venning, Julia E. papers, 1896-1903 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Venning, Louise S.: Diploma for Girls High School of Philadelphia, 1898; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Venning, Louise S.: Trial Teacher's Certificate for School District of Philadelphia, 1900; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Venning, Louise S.: Teacher's certificate for the School District of Philadelphia, 1902; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Venning, Richard DeReef: correspondence, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Holden, William B.: Rent book with newspaper clippings, circa 1911 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Venning, Lillie: Diploma for South Philadelphia High School, 1921; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Venning, George Edward papers, 1923-1976 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Venning, Louise: letter to "Sal" [found with fans, see box 7], 1923 August 29 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Venning, Louise: fans, circa 1923 (Box 7)
  - Holden, William B.: Pequot Club Annual Dinner at Marion Tea Room invitation, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Holden, Sarah Venning: letters received upon the death of her husband, 1928 January-March (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Holden, Sarah Venning: letters received upon the death of her husband, 1928 February (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Holden, Sallie S.: Common Prayer book, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Holden, Sarah S.: First Penny Savings Bank, Philadelphia, account book, 1929-1933 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Venning family invitations, 1932-1937 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Venning, Oliver papers, 1939, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Venning family: Pamphlets and brochures, 1939, 1955, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Venning, George E. and Sarah S. Holden: Western Savings Fund Society account book, 1946-1951 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Venning, Miranda: Biography notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Venning, Sallie Sanders: "The Rose Elf" story, December, 1888 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - State Gazette of South Carolina, 1792 (Box 8, Folder 20, Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Deed from Margaret S. Jenson to Richard DeReef Venning for property at 18th and Fitzwater Streets, Philadelphia, 1902; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Property documents for Sallie S. Holden, George E. Venning, and Julia Venning [17282.Q], 1946, 1951.; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "Victorian African Americans: A Newspaper Education Supplement," Philadelphia Inquirer [17282.Q], 9 February 1988.; [Oversized] (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Series V. Unattributed family papers
  - [Venning family papers?]: State Gazette of South Carolina, 1792 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - [Unknown owner]: South Carolina document making Isaac Mott Dark a Justice of the Peace, 1802 (Box 8, Folder 11)